in this run method, we will create a game loop which will be the core of our game
first we create this while loop
this means
as long as this gameThread exists, it repeats the process that is written inside of this brackets
so to test that, let's display some texts
let's call this method, maybe from here
let's check it
so as you can see, the program is repeating this process
this is just a testing but in the actual game, there are two things that we're gonna do in this loop
the one is update
the other one is...
for example, let's say your player character is at x 100 and y 100 on the screen
if player hit the down key which should make the player character go down
so maybe we add 3 to the y coordinate
so player's y coordinate is 103 now
and that means we updated the player information
then based on this updated information, we redraw the screen
now we draw the player character at x 100 and y 103
so if player keeps pressing the down key
we keep updating the character's y-coordinates like 106, 109, 112, 115
and redrawing the character with the updated coordinates
so we repeat this. check the update and draw the screen
if we set the game's FPS as 30, we do this update and draw 30 times per second
and if FPS is 60, we do this 60 times per second
and to do this update and draw we create two methods
the one is called update
and the other one is called paintComponent
this paintComponent is actually a built-in method in Java so this is not my original name or anything
so it's one of the standard methods to draw things on JPanel
there are other ways to draw but this time we will use this paintComponent
and we also use this Graphics class
we receive Graphics as g
and then add this line
it's just a format whenever you use this paintComponent method on JPanel, you need to type this
this "super" means the parent class of this class
and in this case, the parent class means JPanel
because this GamePanel is a subclass of JPanel
it's a practice that is set by Java to make this work
so we created this method, update and paintComponent
now let's go back to our game loop
and call these two methods
first type update
and then type repaint
not paintComponent but repaint
it's a bit confusing
but that's how you call this paintComponent method
so now as long as this game loop continues, it keeps calling this update and repaint
update and repaint and update and repaint
so let's draw something on the screen
and to draw something we use this paintComponent and this Graphics class
so imagine this Graphics is your pencil or paintbrush
and before using this Graphics
we're gonna convert this Graphics to Graphics2D class
so this means we change this Graphics g to this Graphics2D class
this Graphics and Graphics2D are kind of similar
but this Graphics2D has a bit more functions
we can use this and draw stuff but this time we're gonna use this Graphics2D glass because it has some functions that i want to use later
so first let's set the color
we're gonna use white for now
then let's draw a rectangle on the screen
this fillRect method is gonna draw a rectangle on the screen
and when you draw something on the screen
this Graphics or Graphics2D asks you its x and y coordinates
and also its width and height of the object
so let's say x is 100 and y is 100
and width...
for the time being we're gonna use this as a player character
so let's use this tile size, so 48 by 48
so width is tile size and height is also tile size
and when the drawing is done, we dispose this Graphics2D
the program still works without this line
but this is a good practice to save some memories
sokay let's see
so we drew a 48 x 48 white color rectangle at x 100 and y 100
so we can draw stuff by using this Graphics2D
now we want to move or control this rectangle
and to do that, we need to accept keyboard input
when player hit WASD keys then the rectangle goes up, down, left, or right
so let's create another class to handle this key input
inside of this "main" package, create a class
and i'm going to name this KeyHandler
add this KeyListener
and it asks you to add this unimplemented methods
this keyTyped, keyPressed, and keyReleased
so whenever you implement this KeyListener you have to add these three methods
and we don't use this keyTyped at all
we only use this keyPressed and keyReleased
so this e.getKeyCode basically returns a number of the key that was pressed
and so we're gonna check
so this means if user press W key
then...okay let's add three more
and also we're gonna create some booleans
and so if the pressed key was W
so this is done for now
so let's take care of this keyReleased
first we get this key code
okay let's copy this and paste
now it's not keyPressed but keyReleased so
if released key was W then upPressed is false
and this is also false
not flase
so that's it about this KeyHandler class for now
let's go back to this GamePanel
so we're gonna instantiate this KeyHandler
and we're gonna add this KeyHandler to this GamePanel
so this GamePanel can recognize key input
and also we add one more line
we're gonna create some variables
and also we gonna decide player speed
and i'm gonna set 4
then we go to this paintComponent method
instead of this 100 100
we're gonna type playerX and playerY here
so now these are not fixed number but variables so we can change player position
so where we change player position?
we're gonna do it inside of this update
keyH means this KeyHandler
so if this upPressed is true
then we want to makes the player character goes up
so minus equal or you can also type like this
it's the same, this is a kind of a short way of typing
we are subtracting this player speed from this player y coordinate
it's gonna be opposite so
in this case this player speed 4 means 4 pixels
so when user hit the down key or S key
then player y coordinates increases by 4 pixels
so whenever player hit these keys
the key input is catched by KeyHandler
and this update method updates the player coordinates
and then after this update it's gonna call this paintComponent
and this paintComponent draws a rectangle with updated player x and y positions
but there is still a problem
i will show you what happens right now
so if i hit, for example S key
the rectangle just disappeared when i hit the key
let me explain what just happened
we created this game loop and this repeats this update and repaint
but since we haven't set any specific interval between each update and draw
your computer does this process as fast as it can
since we are just drawing a simple rectangle right now
it's not heavy at all for modern computers' CPU
so probably it can repeat the process like a million times per second
so when we run this program and hit down key
the rectangle moves like several millions pixels for a second
and since this window has only several hundred pixels width and height
the rectangle quickly went out of the frame
and that's why it looked like the rectangle just disappeared
so what we need to do is setting kind of a restriction
we order the program like,
"hey slow down, just update and draw the screen 60 times per second and no more"
and to do that, first we need to know what time it is now
then we also need to know how much time has passed
between here and after this update and the repaint
so without this information we cannot tell our program when to update or draw
and to check the current time we type like this
so we will use nanosecond to check the current system time
nano is a very very small unit and basically 1 billion nanoseconds is equal to 1 second
we can also use this one too
and this returns current time in milliseconds
this is okay too, but nano is more precise
so let me show you an example
let's display the current time
alright let's check it
so this is the current system time in nanosecond
as you can see the time is increasing
so whenever we need to check the current time we can do it by typing like this
okay next let's set FPS for our game
and i think 60 FPS is decent enough so we choose that
after this
let's delete this
now a little bit complicated part
how to create this restriction to make 60 FPS happens?
there are several ways to construct a decent game group
and i will introduce two popular ones here
both are established methods and widely used
i tested both and confirmed both works fine
so you can choose whichever you want
let's start the first one. i call this "sleep method"
first we create variables, outside of this while loop
divided by FPS
yeah that's a lot of zeros
actually it has nine zeros so it's one billion and this means one second
so we use nanoseconds as a calculation unit in this game loop
so it's one second but also one billion nanoseconds
maybe it's a little bit confusing at first but it's all for precise calculation
so we are dividing one second or one billion nanoseconds by 60
so which is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7... divided by 60
equal sixteen million
666... uh nanoseconds or 1 divided by 60
it's the same thing so 0.01666 seconds
so that's the draw interval
so this means we draw the screen every 0.016 seconds
so we can draw the screen 60 times per second
and then next variable
so as we did earlier this System.nanotime returns the current system time
so let's say if we just draw the screen right now
then the next draw time will be the current time plus this drawInterval
so 0.016 seconds later
so we can tell our program
when your internal system time hit this time then draw the screen again
and after setting this nextDrawTime the game loop starts
and the program does this update and repaint
and at this point some time must have passed since this point
so what we need to know is
after this update and repaint
how much time left until the next draw time
so let's check it
so we subtract the current time from nextDrawTime
so this returns how much time remaining until the nextDrawTime
and we need to let the thread sleep for the remaining time
so we type like this
but since this sleep method accepts only "long"
so we're gonna cast this
and also i think we need to surround this with try and catch
and also we're gonna move this remainingTime too to this try and catch
so this sleep basically pause the game loop
so it won't do anything until this sleep time is over
but there is another catch here
as you can see from this description
this sleep method accepts numbers as millisecond
and since we have done these calculations with nanosecond
we need to convert this remainingTime from nano to millisecond
so we divide this remainingTime by one million
so now we can accept this remainingTime as milliseconds
yeah it's a bit confusing
but that's how you do when you use this nanotime and also this sleep method
also we add this if statement
so if this update and repaint took more than this drawInterval
then no time is left
this thread doesn't need to sleep since we already used the allocated time
so we put 0 to the remainingTime
i doubt this will happen in our little 2D game but just in case
and finally
when sleep time is over and the thread is awakened
we're gonna set a new nextDrawTime
so basically we're gonna add drawInterval
which means 0.01666 seconds later will be the nextDrawTime
okay so i think this game loop is done
so let's check it
okay so i'm gonna press S key
D key
W key, A key
it's working so our game loop is working beautifully
and we can move player character now
yeah so this is all good but
let me introduce another game loop
and this is so-called "delta" or "accumulator" method
this is another popular method to create a decent game loop
now i'm gonna just comment out
FPS, this is the same
and then we're gonna create this delta variable
and 0 for now
okay so i'm gonna type everything first
yeah that's it so let's check it
it's working
so at the beginning of the loop we check the currentTime
and then we subtract this lastTime from this currentTime
so which basically means how much time has passed
and also divide it by this drawInterval
and add it to this delta
and the currentTime becomes lastTime
and this if statement
this 1 is equal to this drawInterval
so what we're doing here is
so every loop we add the past time divided by drawInterval to delta
and when this delta reached this drawInterval
then we update and repaint then reset this delta
so this is another way to update and draw at every drawInterval
and to check if this is really drawing the screen 60 times per second
we can display FPS
so to check FPS, we're gonna add a bit more variable
whenever it updates and repaint we increase this drawCount by 1
and we increase the timer
so this means the past time
so in every loop we add the past time to this timer
and when this timer reached 1 second
so 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9...
one billion nanoseconds
we're gonna show FPS
so how many time it updated and repainted until this time hits one second
and then we're gonna reset this drawCount and timer
okay let's check it
yeah like this
so you can see the program is maintaining 60 FPS
so the program is drawing the screen 60 times per second
so this is working good
so we succeeded to create our game loop
and in this tutorial we will continue with this delta game loop
but you can choose either this sleep method or delta method
either way is fine
and we are not gonna edit these game loops anymore so both work just fine throughout this tutorial
some people prefer this delta to this sleep method
because, i'm not really sure but, some say this thread sleep is not completely accurate
so sometimes it creates a few milliseconds difference or something
i'm not really sure about it
maybe you can try both
and see which works better for your game
okay so now the complicated part is done
so next we are going to create a player character
and display player sprites on the screen
[Music]