hi guys, this is RyiSnow
last time, we implemented boots that increase the player speed
and also implemented the music and sound effects
in this video, we will add on-screen UI
and complete this simple treasure hunting game
so let's start
but first, let me edit the current code a little bit since i found a little bug
we used this Sound class for both playing music and sound effects
but i guess that wasn't a good idea
i've noticed, when the program tries to stop a music and play a sound effect at the same time
it only process one of them, not both
like, it plays sound effect but the music doesn't stop
so i decided to instantiate one more Sound class
name this "Music"
and the other one is renamed to SE
and call them separately
so for playing music and stoping music, we call this "music"
and for playing SE, we use this "se"
this way, even if we try to stop a music and play a sound effect at the same time, these classes handle it separately
okay let's continue
first, we create a new class inside of this "main" package
and i'm gonna name this UI
and this class basically handle all the on-screen UI
so we can display text message and item icons or stuff like that
and the constructor
so what are we gonna draw?
since we get keys to open doors, let's display the number of the keys that player currently has
and we can draw texts with this Graphics2D
but first, we need to set up font
to do that, we use this setFont method and pass a font here
you can set a font by typing like this
the first parameter is the font name
so you can use whatever font you want as long as it is supported by your computer
and the second parameter is font style
so you can choose PLAIN or ITALIC or BOLD...
so you can choose a font style
and the third parameter is font size
so usually this is how you set the font on this Graphics2D
but i don't recommend to create a new instance in game loop
because creating instance takes time
this draw method will be included in the game loop, so this will get called 60 times per second
and that means, it will create this new instance 60 times per second
and it will consume time and resource
so this is actually a bad example
so instead we declare the font here
so font and the name is like Arial 40 or something
then instantiate it
so we can finish the instantiation before the game loop starts
so now we just need to type the font name here
then we choose a font color
i'm going to choose white
okay now let's draw some text
and the first parameter is text, and x and y
so for the text, it will be like this
we're gonna display key number so...
okay this needs to be "public"
and x and y
maybe somewhere around here
now let's go to this GamePanel
and instantiate the UI class
somewhere around here
and pass this GamePanel
then inside of this paintComponent, we call the draw method
since usually UI comes at the top of the layers
so UI shouldn't be hidden by tiles or player, right?
so we call it after this player
okay let's check this
so the text is displayed
but there is a catch here
although we typed x50 and y50, but this doesn't look like it
that's because this drawString's y-coordinate works in a bit different way
usually in Java, when you set y, it indicates the top of the image or object
but for some reason,
when you use drawString the y indicates not the top but the baseline of the text
so drawImages y and drawString's y indicate different spots
so this is really confusing
if it indicates a bottom of the object, it's still relatively easy to handle
but as you can see from this image, the baseline is not the bottom
it's somewhere slightly higher than the bottom
i don't know why it works this way but sadly that's how it works
so we need to keep this in mind and adjust the position
so maybe i want to move this to the left a little bit
so i think i'm going to decrease this x a little bit
yeah i think i like this better
but still this looks kind of too generic
so i think it might be better if we display a key image instead of this text
and we can get it from this OBJ_Key class
but again, don't instantiate the class here
instead, let's declare a BufferedImage here
and then instantiate the key class here
and get the key image
so we can prepare this image before the game loop starts
then we're gonna draw this image
and x and y will be something like half tile size
something like this
so it means 24 pixels
so after this image we add a text
we don't need this but instead something like this
so x is 24+48, so 72
we add 2 pixel space
and Y is... i don't know, let's check
so bit lower
maybe 65 or something
yeah something like this
okay looks good
now let's display some notification message
when we pick up these keys or boots or when we try to open the door
so inside of this UI class, we create some variables
the default is false
blank for now
and then create a method
we get a String
and now go to this Player class
when we get the key...
we don't need this System.out.println anymore
so when we get the key, we call this showMessage method
and pass some text... whatever you want to display
so like "you got a key!"
so this method receives the text, and put it in this message string
and change this messageOn to "true"
now inside of this draw method, we create an if statement
then we draw the message
so i wanna display it somewhere around here
half tileSize or something
but basically you can type any number so it's totally up to you
5 tiles to the bottom
and also maybe reduce the font size a little bit
so we can create another font and change the size
but if a font is already set, we can change the size by typing like this
so we get the current font and then...
and here we type number and it accepts "float" so we add "f"
alright let's check this
so the message is displayed but right now, it keeps staying on the screen
so i think it would be better if the message disappears after a while
so let's do that
we're gonna create another variable
and start from 0
so every time this draw method gets called, we increase the counter
when the counter hits a certain number, we stop displaying the text
so this means 120 frames
and this is 60 frames per second so this means 2 seconds
so the text disappears after 2 seconds
so let's check this
[Music]
yeah looks good
let's add some more text
when you open the door...
"You opened the door!"
also, when you don't have a key...
okay let's create "else"
"You need a key!"
and when you get the boots... "Speed up!"
okay let's check
alright looking good
so now we only need to take care of this treasure chest
so let's create the final case
so if you get this treasure chest, you beat the game
so we want to stop the game
let's go to the UI class
and in this UI class, we need to tell the program the game is finished
and the default is false
and go back to this Player class
and when you get this treasure chest...
and also we're gonna stop the music
and play a sound effect
so this one... "fanfare"
so the index is 4
not playerSE
playSE
let's not forget to "break"
in this UI class, we check if the game is finished or not
then we do something
so we put everything else in this "else"
okay here, we're gonna display some congratulations kind of message
and we want to display this message around the center of the screen
we can find out the coordinates of the center by typing like this
but this doesn't work because, this means the text starts from here
so the text will be displayed at the right side of the screen
so we need to do a little adjustment
first, we find out the length of the text that we're gonna display
so let me create some more variables
like this
also let's copy these two lines
we need to set a font and a font color
and we input some text
"You found the treasure!"
now we're gonna check the length of this text
to do that...
and here, first we're gonna pass this text
and the context is g2
it looks a bit complicated but basically this returns the length of this text
and now we subtract... the half of this text length
so this way the text will be aligned to the center
let's adjust this y coordinates as well
because the player character is displayed at the center
and i don't want to hide him with the text
so we decrease the Y a little bit
we can adjust it later
so we can finally draw the string
the first one is text and x and y
we're gonna display one more line, "congratulations"-kind of message
and for this one i think we're gonna use a bit larger font
first let's declare another font
and we're gonna use not PLAIN but BOLD
i'm gonna name this "80B" so it's easy to understand what it is
and instantiate the font
the size is 80 and the style is BOLD
after displaying this "You found the treasure!"...
okay let's copy this
so change it to arial_80B
and let's change the font color as well
i think we can copy this and the paste
the text is "Congratulations!"
and get the text length
x is the same and we only need to adjust this y
so this time, we gonna display a bit lower than the center
so not minus but plus... probably 2 tiles
and finally, we're gonna stop the game
so after drawing these strings, we're gonna call this gameThread and put "null"
so this stops the thread
we are done
let's check
everything works good
we found three keys, opened three doors, and found the treasure
so basically this is it, but i want to add a final touch
what we're gonna do is, displaying the playtime on the screen
so you can see how long it took to find the treasure
so inside of this UI class...
we use double so we can display decimal too
i think that's more interesting
somewhere around here i think
we gonna add 1/60 seconds to this playTime
this draw method gets called 60 times per second
so we add 1/60 seconds in every loop
then we're going to display the time on the screen
i think i want to display it around here so
and screen width is 16 tiles so... minus 5?
11 tiles to the right
we're going to use the same y-coordinates as this key
something like this
okay let's check this
so the playtime is displayed
but so many decimals
this doesn't look so good
so let's format this number a little bit
and to format this decimal values, there is a nice class
so we're gonna use this class to format
and inside of this constructor we can type like this
so this means, we display up to tow places of decimals
so if you want to display three, then you can type like this
and let's edit this
not just playtime but we use this dFormat
so let's check this
alright
and finally, i wanna display your playtime when you finish the game
so let's copy
the place is... around here
plus 3 tiles i guess
maybe 4
i guess this is everything
okay so let's check
so how long it's gonna take
[Music]
i think this is the fastest route
so first you get the boots
and get two other keys
[Music]
oh come on
i'm losing time
okay so my time was 35.93 seconds
alright
let me try this again
i think i can do this better
[Music]
alright
looking good
okay looks good
oh
much better, 31.70 seconds
okay so that's it
you know the game is pretty straightforward
but depending on how you construct your map or game
you might be able to enjoy kind of intense time attack gameplay or something
anyway, this is the end of the first half of this Java 2D game tutorial
thank you so much for watching
in the second half we will add a lot more elements
such as NPCs and monsters and the battle...
and change this into action RPG
so if you are interested please keep watching
i promise it will be pretty good
alright that's it for now
thanks again and until next time
[Music]