hi guys, this is RyiSnow
last time, we created some objects and displayed them on the screen
but now, nothing happens even if you touch it
so this time, we will implement object collision and also the reactions of these objects
we've already done tile collision so we use this CollisionChecker class again
but this time, we use a different method to check collision
and to check object collision, we need to do a little preparation
first, open this Entity class
and after this solidArea, we're gonna add two integer variable
and go to this Player class
we add this solidAreaDefaultX
so basically, defaultX is this one
the reason we do this is, we want to record the default values
because we're gonna change these x and y values later
and go to this SuperObject
and here, we create a Rectangle and instantiate it
so like player character, each object has this solidArea
and i use the default value
so basically, the whole tile, all this object tile is solid
but if you want to set the specific solidArea for each object, you can do that
in that case, for example, you open this OBJ_Key and...
something like this
but this time, we don't set specific solidArea for each object
but all the objects use the same this solidArea
and in this case, 0
this is also 0
let's open this Door class
we want to make this solid so we add...
okay i think that's all for the preparation
so let's go to this CollisionChecker
we're gonna create a new method
this time, not checkTile but checkObject
also this method is not void but the integer
and we receive an Entity
and also a boolean
i'm gonna name this player
first we receive an Entity, so player or maybe other characters
and also we're gonna check if this Entity is player or not
and since this is "int", we need to return integer
so first, we create this integer
and name this "index"
and return this index
so what we do in this method is, we check if player is hitting any object
and if he is, we return the index of the object
so we can process the reaction accordingly
okay next, we create a for loop
we're gonna scan this object array
yeah this one
then first, we check if it is "null" or not
if it's not null,
then we need to know the Entity's solidArea posision
also, we need to get the object's solidArea position
okay
last time, we tried to find out this column and the row numbers
but this time, we don't need to do that
we only need to find out the solidArea's x and y
then we're going to find out the object's x and y
so basically it's the same
yeah that's it
so we found out entity's and object's solidArea position
and now, we create a switch and check the Entity's direction
so after it goes up, where it will be?
we find it out so...
since it's going up so minus y
and if it's going down...
and if it's going left then...
so this is the y position this entity will be after it moved
this rectangle class has a beautiful method called "intersects"
let me type first
so you can type like this
this automatically checks if these two rectangles are colliding or not
to use this intersects we needed to find out these solidAreas' current position
if the Entity is touching this object then uh...
okay so for testing, let's show some text
"up collision!" or something
so basically we can copy this to each case
alright and after this switch statement, we need to reset this entity's and object's solidArea
otherwise this x and y keep increasing
so we need to reset these numbers after this switch statement
this time we can use this...
okay
yeah this is okay for now
let's call this checkObject method
so go to this Player class
and after checking this tile collision, we're gonna check object collision
and pass this Player class as an Entity
and player boolean is... since this is player so the boolean is true
ah and also, since this returns index as an integer so let's get it
like this
but before using this, let's check the current program
and see if the collision is really working or not
touching a key. up, left, right... and down
up
right
left
okay so it's working
so let's remove this text
and instead, another if statement
so we're gonna check if this object is a solid object or not
so first, we check it and if it's solid then...
also we're gonna check if this is player or not
so this one is boolean
if this is player, we get this index and return it
but if it's not player, for example, if it is an NPC or a monster then we don't do anything
and we can copy this and paste
alright, i think this method is done
yeah like i said, this method is different from this checkTile method
i like this intersects
it's very convenient and clean
so maybe you think, why I didn't use this for checking tile collision as well
the reason i didn't use this for tile collision is
for this object, we only need to scan a limited number of object
in this case, up to 10 objects so it doesn't take much
but if we do this for background tiles, we basically need to scan all the tiles on the screen
and check one by one if any of them is touching this entity's solidArea
that's okay and i believe our program still works just fine
but if we use our current method, we only need to check two tiles for each direction
so that's why i didn't use intersects for checking tiles
but it really depends i think
either way works so it really depends on how your game is constructed
alright, this is done so let's go back to this Player class
then based on this index number, we type what's going to happen if player touches this object
we can type it here but i think it would be better if we handle it in a separated method
so we create a new method
after this, i think
and we get an index
so let's call this and pass objIndex
okay and first, create an if statement
if this index is 999, that means we didn't touch any object
but if the index is not 999, then we have touched an object
so we can do something about it
and i think the simplest reaction would be like this
this simply delete the object that we just touched
so let's see how it looks
yeah, like this
so the key just disappeared
but of course, this reaction is just too simple
so let's set specific reactions on each object
okay first, let's create an integer
i'm gonna name this "hasKey"
so this indicates how many keys the player currently has
go back to this pickUpObject
so we don't need this anymore
we get this object name
we have input a name so it's time to use this
so we got a name
and the case is "Key"
and also "Door"
if it was "Key" then hasKey++
we want to make it disappear
let's take care of this door too
so first, we check if player has a key or keys
so this door object will disappear
like this
okay, let's display some information on console
so we know how many keys we have right now
yeah let's check this
let me see the console
let's get the key
okay now let's open the door
open the door
and we cannot open this one because we have no key
so we need to get another key to open this door
i think this is working good
so now the player can get keys and open doors
but still, this is a very simple way to handle objects' reactions
we will create more organized system to handle this in the second chapter of this tutorial series
like, getting items in your inventory and stuff like that
but for now this should be enough
okay, so that's it for now
in the next video, we will add one more item, music, and sound effect
thanks for watching and until next time
[Music]