yeah like this
so you can see the program is maintaining 60 fps so this is working good
okay now we are going to create Player class
first, create another package
and i'm gonna name this "entity"
so we're gonna create all the character class
player, monster, npc, stuff like that
then inside of this entity package
create a class called Entity
and this will be the parent class for the Player class and any other character classes
and inside of this Entity class we create some variables
okay so that's it for now
now let's create the Player class
so inside of this entity package, create Player
and this extends Entity
and we're gonna use this GamePanel class
and also KeyHandler
so import...this one i think
and constructor
and we get GamePanel, also KeyHandler
and go back to this GamePanel class
we're gonna instantiate this Player class
and we're gonna pass this GamePanel class and KeyHandler
so now we can use this GamePanel and KeyHandler in this Player class
and then we're gonna create a method
and inside we're gonna set the player's default values
and the first, x equal 100 for now
and y equal 100
and speed equal 4
so maybe you have noticed
what we are doing here is the same as what we did inside of this GamePanel class
but this was just for testing
although we update the player information and draw the player in this GamePanel class
right now it's only about the player
but in the future we will update and draw more stuff like background tiles or monsters or npcs
if we type everything here, then it's going to be a huge chunk of code
you can do that but it would be better if we can handle it in a bit more organized way
so we create this update method in this Player class too
and also draw method
and we copy everything inside of this update
copy... or move everything here
and also this one
we're gonna move these two lines to inside of this draw method
and here, we just type
so we just call this method inside of this Player class
and make sure to pass this Graphics2D
without this we cannot draw anything
so we receive this Graphics2D here
so now we can use this g2 inside of this Player class too
now we are seeing some errors so we need to do a little adjustment
so this time instead of this playerY, playerX, or playerSpeed
we will use y and x and speed
we're gonna just use tileSize in this GamePanel class
okay i think we need to make this public
this needs to be public so otherwise the Player class cannot access this
so we named this just x, y, and speed
not playerX, playerY, playerSpeed
because other non-player characters also use these variables
also let's call this method from this constructor
so we're gonna set these default values
okay so let's check this
so the rectangle is moving just like before
but moving a rectangle is not that fun
so let's replace it with character sprites
i prepared this so these are the player character sprites that i made
i prepared 8 images. 2 for down and 2 for left
and 2 for right and 2 for up
2 images for each direction so we can create a little animation
i know my pixel art skill is pretty rudimentary so i think you can create better one
to create these sprites you can use any software
you can use Paint, Photoshop, Gimp, anything is fine
maybe i will create a little video to show how i make these sprites later
just make sure that the size is 16 by 16 and the background is transparent
and save it as PNG
we're going to create a "res" folder
and inside of this we're going to create a package
we'll name this "player"
we're gonna copy these images to this player package
so now let's go to this Entity
and we add another variables
and another variable
and import BufferedImage
okay let's go to this Player class
and now let's create another method
and inside of this try and catch we're gonna load these images
and inside of this bracket we type the file path
and since it's inside of this player package in this res folder
so let's copy
okay and let's call this method
also let's set the default direction
inside of this if statement we add direction information
so if up is pressed, direction is up
and if down is pressed, direction is down
and go to this draw method
we're not gonna use this anymore
we're not gonna use this rectangle
create a switch statement or an if statement... either way is fine
we're gonna check direction
if direction is up...
and if direction is down...
so these are these BufferedImages we loaded a while ago
so based on this direction we pick a different image
and finally we're gonna draw images
we're gonna type x and y
and also type width and height
so we're gonna just use this tileSize
this is called the ImageObserver and you just can type "null" here
so we're gonna draw image at x and y with this size
so let's check this
so this Blue Boy appeared
the player character appeared
so now instead of white rectangle we can control this blue boy
but it doesn't look like he's walking
he's more like skidding or something
that's because we only used this up1, down1, left1, right1
we haven't used this up2, down2, left2, right2
so next we will use this number two images too and create a working animation
let's go to this Entity class again
and start from zero
go back to this Player class
inside of this draw method we're gonna add a little if statement
i think i'm gonna just copy
and now we're gonna create a simple sprite changer or something like that
so inside of this update, first we're going to add spriteCounter
and after that we reset this spriteCounter
let me explain a little bit
this update method gets called 60 times per second
uh here
because this is inside of this game loop. this gets called 60 times per second
so in every frame this gets called and increases this counter by 1
and if it hits 10
it changes the sprite
so 1 to 2 or 2 to 1
it means the player image changes in every 10 frames
and it's gonna draw image1 or image2 on the screen
so let's check this
hmm
okay so maybe 10 is a bit too fast so change this to 12
okay i think
but there is still a little issue here
as you can see the player character is moving when you are not pressing any keys
if you feel okay with this then okay
actually some retro games are like this
but if you don't like this we can fix this
right now the spriteCounter increases every time this update gets called
but we're gonna add this if statement
and we're gonna move everything inside of this if statement
so now this spriteCounter increases only when you are pressing one of these keys
so the player sprite doesn't change unless you press a key
yeah let's check this
so right now he's not moving
but if you press a key
he moves like this
okay so now our player character is moving
so next i think we're gonna implement background tiles
so not this black background anymore
so let's do that
[Music]