hi guys, this is RyiSnow
so last time we succeeded to draw these background tiles
but this is just a small sample map and the size is only as large as the game screen
if single screen is all you need for your game, this might be okay
but what we are trying to create, ultimately, in this tutorial is a 2D action RPG
so we want to have a larger map
so in this video we will create a world map and draw it on the screen
and to create a world map, i have prepared a few extra tiles
tree, sand, and earth (dirt)
so let's copy these to this "tiles" package
and let's load these new tiles
so let's copy this and add three more
now we can use these tiles too
and this is the world map i created
it's a 50 by 50 tile map
of course you can create your own map
and if you want to create a larger map, you can do that
and before loading and drawing this world map file, we need to do some adjustment
what we're gonna do is, we edit the code in the Player class
so instead of moving around on the screen
the player character will always be displayed at the center
and we will expand the boundary of our tile drawing loop
our current tile drawing system is set for drawing tiles as large as our screen size
and that's not enough to draw our world map so we change it
and when these two steps are done we can display our world map and move around it
so let's get to the step one
let's go to this Entity class
and we're gonna rename this x and y to worldX and worldY
how to say... just for better understanding
because we are going to use two kinds of x and y
the one is worldX and worldY
and this one is screenX and screenY
these are different and indicate different coordinates
and understanding this difference will be the key to understand the mechanics of game camera
okay then let's go to this Player class
and the rename this x and y too
wait what
what is this
sorry
and this one too
we leave this for now
because we're gonna use a different kind of x and y here
so in this Player class, rename this x and y in the setDefaultValues
and also x and y in this update method
and this worldX and worldY are not screen position
this is not where we draw on the screen
this is the player's position on the world map
and i want to change this default player position
so this is going to be the starting point
i want to start the game at this point
so this is gonna be... 23
so instead of this 100 100 we're gonna type...
this is gonna be the starting position
then in this Player class, we create another x and y variables
so now we have worldX, worldY and screenX, screenY
and screenX and screenY indicate where we draw player on the screen
so we place this player character at the center of the screen and scroll the background as he moves
that's what we're gonna do
so this returns the halfway point of the screen
so when we draw this player character,
instead of this x and y, let's replace them with screenX and screenY
this screenX and screenY don't change throughout the game
these are "final" variables
so the player character's screen position doesn't change
okay let's check this
so now player's position is fixed at the center of the screen or...
actually, this is not the center of the screen
these two variables indicate the center of the screen for sure
but the problem is, these coordinates are used for the top left corner of the image
so we need to do a little adjustment
from this value we're going to subtract...
and this too
alright let's check
can you see the difference?
now the player character is displayed at the center of the screen
so the step one is done
let's get to the step two
let's go to this GamePanel and we create some world map parameters
as i said you can change these numbers as you like
i think this GamePanel class is okay
so let's go to the TileManager class
and we're gonna change the size of this mapTileNum too
we're gonna change this from maxScreenCol to maxWorldCol
and this is also maxWorldRow
and let's change this file path too
and in this loadMap method,
we're gonna change maxScreenCol to maxWorldCol
and maxScreenRow to maxWorldRow
so basically we are doing a larger loop here
so in the previous loop, the screen size was the boundaries
but now the world map is the boundaries
now we move on to the draw method and do some arrangement
and this is gonna be a little bit complicated because we're gonna implement a camera function
first we're gonna delete this x and y
so we're not gonna use this x and y in this loop
and delete this and this and this too
then we're gonna change this col and row to worldCol and worldRow
so copy this worldCol and paste here
and also let's change this maxScreenCol to maxWorldCol
and now a tricky part
ultimately, there are three things that we want to know
tile image and where to draw the tile on the screen
and we already know what kind of tile image it is going to display
and to find out this x and y, we type like this:
wait... this is not public?
why i'm seeing the error
oh okay, sorry
we need to set this as public
then one more variable
why i always type like this...
and we're gonna paste this screenX and screenY here
let me explain about this part
first we check the tile's worldX
so that is worldCol x tileSize
so
if it's a [0][0] tile,
it's gonna be a 0 x 48 and 0 x 48
so x and y are also 0 0
and if it's a [1][0] tile,
which means this one
then worldX will be 1 x 48 so worldX will be 48
and worldY is still 0
then we need to know where on the screen we need to draw it
again, this screenX is different from worldX
worldX is the position on the map
and screenX is where on the screen we draw it
imagine, if player is at worldX 500 and worldY 500
then player is 500 pixels away from this [0][0] tile
let's say it's around here
then this [0][0] tile should be drawn at 500 pixels to the left and 500 pixels to the top from the player
that's why we subtract the player's worldX and worldY from the tile's worldX and worldY
and that returns the tile's screen position
so if player's position is 500:500 then this tile's screen position will be the x minus 500 and y minus 500
so basically it's out of our game window
then why we add this player's screenX and screenY?
there is a little catch here
so remember, the player's screen position is always at the center of the screen
for example, screenX 0 and screenY 0 means the top left corner
here
and it becomes minus (from here)
so 0:0 is here
even if player is standing at worldX 0 and worldY 0
still, he is displayed at the center of the screen
not here
so we need to offset this difference
so we add this to the calculation
adding this, we can offset the difference
and we can get correct coordinates for this tile's screenX and screenY
i hope you understand and it's okay even if you still feel "uh... what?"
i was like that, it took me a while to wrap my head around this
so it's okay for now, just copy and paste this code
but i hope you will get it eventually and i think you will
and i hope my explanation was enough
yeah this is complicated
anyways so we found out a tile's screenX and screenY
so after drawing a tile we increase this worldCol by 1
so we can draw the next tile
and if worldCol hits this maxWorldCol...
yeah we draw one by one
and when we hit this tile
we reset col and increase row so we move here
and draw this line and this line...
okay so this should work now so let's check it
i hope this works
so now we are exploring the world now
so this is the world map that i created
of course, there is no collision yet
so this is working
but we can add a little more touch to improve our rendering efficiency
you can continue as it is
but i recommend you to do this to avoid a slow game performance
maybe you have noticed but right now this while loop is drawing all the tiles on the map
that means it is drawing tiles that we cannot see on the screen too
and that's not so efficient
this is still a relatively a small map
but when you have a very large map, it can slow the game down
so we only need to draw the tiles that we can see
we don't need to draw a tile which is 500 pixels away from the player
so this is the final touch
with this our tile drawing system will be complete so please stick with me
so before drawing a tile we add this if statement
and we're gonna put this drawImage method in this if statement
okay that's it
what this if statement means is, basically we create a boundary
that is from the center of the screen minus player screenX
and plus player screenX
and minus player screenY, and plus player screenY
so as long as a tile is in this boundary, we draw it
so let's check this
okay, like this
so now we can see that the program is only drawing the tiles around the player
but i guess we should expand the boundary a bit more since we are seeing the black background
so why don't we expand this boundary by 1 tile to each direction
to do that, we just...
i don't like this format for some reason...
okay so to do that, we add this worldX and tileSize
and this one is...
okay this should be okay
so let's check this
now it looks the same as before
but actually it's only drawing the tiles around the player so we can cut some extra processing
so now the program is drawing the world map and we can move around it
but of course, there is no collision happening yet
so every tile is passable
so next time, we will implement collision detection
thanks for watching and see you again
[Music]