hi guys, this is RyiSnow
in this video I will talk about the rendering performance of our 2D game and introduce a way to improve it
in the first half of the tutorial, we only draw tiles, a few objects, player character, and UI
but we're gonna handle a bit more heavy stuff in the second half
so I think it's a good idea to optimize our code a little bit
so first let's check how long our program is taking to draw stuff
so this is a debug stuff
so again we're gonna use this System.nonoTime to check the time
then after drawing these components
let's display the past time on the screen
and i wanna display this on the console too
something like this
so this way we can check how much time has passed and display the time on the screen
and since this is a debug function, i think it would be better if we can switch it on and off
so open this KeyHander
i'm gonna use T as a shortcut key
also we're gonna create a boolean
so we only check this time
put this inside of this if
this one too
okay like this
let's check
so if you press T key, t shows the time
so now we can see how long this is taking to draw stuff during each loop
in my case it is taking about...
the fastest is like 622,000 nanoseconds
to 700,000 or 900,000 sometimes
so that means....
0.0007 seconds
not bad
but I think this time changes depending on the computer
so if there is a way to decrease this time, we better do that
in my UI tutorial I said you shouldn't create a new instance in game loop unless it's really necessary
and there is another thing that we can prepare beforehand
that is scaling
so every time we draw tiles or sprites we type this width and height
so the image is displayed as a scaled size
so this image scaling is a pretty convenient function of Graphics or Graphics2D
but it also takes a little time
so let's scale these images beforehand so Graphics2D can skip this process
so we're gonna scale these tile images when we import them
basically this is how to scale BufferedImages
and first I will show you step by step
for example, if we want to scale this image we type like this
and import BufferedImage
yeah this is basically it
first we instantiate this BufferedImage
so this is basically like a blank canvas
so when you instantiate it you pass its width and height and image type
and next line...
this line basically means whatever this g2 is gonna draw will be saved in this scaled image
so in the next line, this g2 draws this image with this scaled size
and so the scaled image will be saved in this scaled image
that's how it is
so if we repeat this to these other tiles then we can scale everything
but typing these lines for every tiles is kind of too much pain and not so efficient
so let's do a little housekeeping and optimize this code a little bit
so we're going to create a new class and let it scale all these buffered images
so in this main package, create a new class
and i'm gonna name this UtilityTool
this is like a toolbox class
so whenever you come up with some a convenient function, you put it in this class and you can call it
and we gonna receive BufferedImage
and basically we can copy and paste it here
and change this to...
and the drawImage is...
and finally we return this scaled image
okay and I think we should dispose this g2 I think
okay so something like this
and we just need to pass the buffered image and the width and height
so go back to the TileManager
delete this
and do a little reconstruction
first we create a method called "setup"
let's instantiate this UtilityTool
and then try and catch
okay and inside of this try and catch, we're gonna instantiate a new tile
let's copy this
change this to index and also and this part
so this part is different
but these parts are always the same so we don't need to change it
we're gonna pass a buffered image and width and height
that's it
so instead of these lines we just type...
file name, path, and collision status
so we don't need this anymore
okay so let's copy this
yeah something like this
so we don't need this anymore
and try and catch too, we don't need these
yeah like this
so we pass index, image name file, image path or more like image name
yeah let's change this to imageName
so image name and collision
so instantiate tile and import the image
and also call this utility tool and get the scaled image
and also set the collision
so yeah I think this looks better
so now all these images are scaled
so go to this draw method
and delete this width the height
so this doesn't need to scale the image during the game loop anymore
and we do the same to play a player image and object image
and for player images we are not using arrays like background tiles
so I think we only need to get the resource and scale it
i think we're gonna just return a buffered image
so it will be something like this
let's copy this
and then scale the image
i feel this is a bit strange
we are calling this scaled image before scaling it
it works but somehow I don't like this
so let's change to just image
i feel better this way for some reason
and finally we return this image
alright then we get this image
so this time we are not using array
this time we are only passing the image name since we don't have index
and also we don't need to set collision
okay so we don't need these lines anymore
and go to draw methos
and delete these width and height
and finally, object
so first open this SuperObject
and instantiate this UtilityTool
and then open this object class
and for this one I think we're gonna just call this UtilityTool and scale the image
yeah I think we need GamePanel
yeah so we get it from here
let's add these to other objects
and okay so
and also go to this AssetSetter
and when we instantiate this object we pass this gp
and what is this? UI class?
that's it
yeah so let's check
let's show the draw time
so now the draw time is something like this
it's like between 430,000 to 650,000 or something
so I think the draw time decreases by maybe 200,000 nanoseconds or something
for now it's not a big difference
but when you use more tiles draw more stuff on the screen
this difference that this kind of optimization creates will become pretty significant
so before moving on to the second half I wanted to introduce this little method
that's it so i hope this was useful for you
thanks for watching
[Music]