hi guys, this is RyiSnow
so last time, we loaded our world map and implemented a camera function
so now we can move around the world
but still, we can walk through these trees and waters
so in this video, we will implement collision detection in our program
so the player won't be able to walk through solid tiles
when we created this Tile class, we created this "collision" boolean
so it's time to use this
first, we go to this TileManager
and look for a tile that we want to change it to a solid tile
for example, this wall tile should be solid
we don't want our player character walk through this tile
we call this collision boolean and set it "true"
also this water tile... this one too
and this one too
and if it's not a solid tile... like this grass tile
then you don't need to add anything because the collision is false as default
so you need to add this only if the tile is solid
ok so tiles' collision setting is done
then we decide which part of the player character is solid and which part is not
the easiest way is setting the whole tile solid
but sometimes it won't produce the best result
for example, if the whole player sprite is soid,
then he hits this wall at this point and cannot move further
but maybe you want to move him a bit further... like this
also, there's another issue
if everything is solid, it's really difficult to get through a narrow path like this
because even if the player is 1 pixel to the left, collision still happens here
so you need to place him very precisely, like this
and that is simply pretty stressful and bad control mechanics, in my opinion
for example, "oh i'm hitting this tile so let's move to the right a little bit"
and "oh now i'm hitting this tile and i still cannot go further"
so to avoid this kind of hassle,
we set a specific area of the character as solid, not everything
like, only this part is solid
then the player can get through this kind of narrow path
and to set this kind of collision area,
first, open this Entity
we use this Rectangle class
and i'm gonna name this solidArea
with this class, we can create an invisible or abstract rectangle
and we can store data such as x, y, width, and height
also, we create a boolean called collisionOn, and the default is false
now go to this Player class
and instantiate that rectangle
wait, oh what is this...
and when we instantiate this rectangle, we can pass 4 parameters to the constructor
for example, if you want to create a rectangle which is the same size as our tiles,
you type like this:
x=0, y=0, widht=48, and height=48
or you can also type like this: gp.tileSize
either way is fine
or we can also leave this blank and set these values one by one
and since we want to make this rectangle a bit smaller than the player character
we change these values a little bit
maybe something like this
so this gray area is not solid, and this area is solid
so this slid area starts from x 8
and width is 32 and height is also 32
so the top left corner is x=8, and y=16
so in that case, we're gonna change this x to 8, and y to 16
and widht is 32 and height is also 32
you can adjust these numbers and find what works best for your game
so we got this collision area for the player character
now let's create a class to check collision
inside this "main" package, create a class
and i'm gonna name this CollisionChecker or whatever name you want
and first, constructor
and we receive GamePanel
and create a method
and we receive Entity here
not Player but Entity
because we will use this method to check not only player collision but also monster and NPC collisions as well
now go to the GamePanel
and instantiate this CollisionChecker class
and pass this GamePanel
and now go to this Player class
and we check collision inside of this update method
after this direction if statement,
first, we set this collisionOn to false
then call this...
oh sorry
this needs to be "public"
so we're gonna call this checkTile method from here
and pass this Player class as Entity
since this Player class is a subclass of this Entity class
so the CollisionChecker can receive the Player class as Entity
alright, now the main part of this video
what we need to do is, to check if the player is hitting a solid tile or not
to do that, first, we want to know the worldX and the worldY of the player's solidArea
not the player's worldX and Y because collision needs to be detected based on these solidArea coordinates
there are 4 points to be checked
and we can find out these 4 numbers like this:
then based on these coordinates, we will find out their column and row numbers
we simply divide it by tileSize
and finally we will create two more integers
because basically, we only need to check two tiles for each direction
if the player is going up,
we only need to check what tiles the player's left shoulder and right shoulder are hitting
so in this case, if the player is going up like this
this is hitting... maybe this wall tile
and this right shoulder is hitting this grass tile
now we're gonna create a switch statement
we're gonna check the entity's direction
so let's take care of this "up" first
for example, the player is here right now
and he is trying to go up
what we are doing here is, we kind of predict where the player will be after he moved
so we subtract this player's speed from the player's worldY
or the player's solidArea's worldY, to be precise
now we know this row number so we can find out what tile the player is trying to step in
and there are possibly two tiles
so we're gonna call this mapTileNum
this stores all the map tile information
oh this also needs to be "public"
and the other one is...
we checked this point, this is tileNum1
now we want to check this point, the right side
with this information, we create an if statement
and call this Tile array... this also needs to be "public"
we're gonna use this tileNum1 as an index
and check if this tile is solid or not
if one of them or both are true, the player is hitting a solid tile
so he cannot move this direction
if these collisions are false, then we don't do anything
ok so this "up" case is done
let's go back to this Player class
and now we're gonna move these player movement lines from here to here
maybe i like this format better...
because now we're checking collision so the player can move only when the tiles are not solid
so first, we only check the direction
and based on this direction, we check collision
and if collision is not happening, we let the player move
ok let's check this
so now this tree tile is stopping the player character
but it's still only the up direction
you can still go left, down, and right
so let's take care of the other directions too
i think we can copy and paste
we only change some variables
so if the player is going down, we're not gonna check the topRow but the bottomRow
so change this to bottomRow
we're gonna change this from top to bottom
and if the player is going left then...
we're gonna check the leftCol
and the leftCol will be...
so now we're gonna check this point and this point
if going right then...
that's it, i think
ok let's check this
ok hitting the tile
and this water tile too
so collision is happening
yup, looks good
so this is getting more and more like a game
so we took care of the collision detection
next time, we will create objects and display them on the screen
so the player can pick them up
thanks for watching, and until next time