hi guys, this is RyiSnow
last time we implemented collision detection
so now, the player character cannot walk through solid tiles
and this time, we will create some objects and display them on the screen
so first, we prepare some object images
okay i think... so this is door
[Music]
something like this... so key
okay something like this
so...treasure chest
[Music]
this is not so bad
okay so this is boots
so i have prepared these four objects
so inside of this "res" folder let's create another package
and i'm gonna name this "objects"
and we're gonna copy these four images to this "objects"
then inside of this source folder, create another package
and name this "object"
inside of this package, create a class
and i'm gonna name this SuperObject
so this will be a parent class of all object classes that we will create later
kind of similar to this Entity class and this Player class
and inside of this SuperObject we declare some classes and object variables
and the default is "false"
and import BufferedImage
alright that's all for now
so let's create an object class
so inside of this object package, create a class
and i'm gonna name it OBJ_Key
you can just type Key but i kind of like adding this kind of abbreviation
so it's really clear that this is an object class
and this OBJ_Key class extends SuperObject
and constructor
and inside of this constructor, first we set the name
and then we're gonna load the image
and here we're gonna type the file path
it's inside of this objects folder so...
okay now let's go to this GamePanel
around here
we're gonna use this SuperObject
and we're gonna use this as an array
the size is... i choose 10
so this 10 means, we prepare 10 slots for object
so we have 10 slots, but we can replace the content during the game
so this doesn't mean we can only create 10 objects in the game
this just means we can display up to 10 objects at the same time
for example, if you pick up an objectA, the objectA disappears from the screen
so we can add a new object in the vacant slot
i just chose 10 because displaying too many objects at the same time can slow down the game
but if you think 10 is not enough, you can always increase this number
you can decide the number as checking your game's performers
alright, next we will instantiate some objects and place them on the map
we can do it in this GamePanel class by creating a method
but i think it would be better to create a specific class and let it handle all the placement stuff
so inside of this "main" package let's create a class
and i'm gonna name this AssetSetter
or whatever name you like
we're gonna use GamePanel
and the constructor
so we're gonna receive GamePanel
okay so inside of this GamePanel let's instantiate this AssetSetter
maybe after this CollisionChecker
and pass this GamePanel class
okay so go back to this AssetSetter
now create a method
so here we're gonna instantiate some default objects and place them on the map
so we're going to use this object array
we're going to use this key object class
since this OBJ_Key is a subclass of this SuperObject class
so you can instantiate it as one of this array
and next
and here we're gonna set this object's worldX and the worldY
i wanna place this key here
in front of this lake or pond
let's open this map file
so this point
okay i'm gonna change this to the grass tile
and so col 23 and row seven
okay let's create one more key
so we're gonna put index 1
so one more key
this time i want to place it around here
so we instantiated these two keys and also set their default location
now let's call this setObject method
go to GamePanel
somewhere around here
i'm gonna name this method setupGame or something like that
so from here we're gonna call setObject
and we want to call this set object method before this game starts
so we're gonna call this setupGame method probably from this Main class
and before starting this game thread so...
yeah so we call this setObject method
and now these key objects get its wordX and worldY
now let's draw these objects on the screen
to draw these objects, we go to this SuperObject class
and create a draw method here
and here we get Graphics2D
and also i think we need GamePanel
alright
what we're gonna do here is almost identical to what we did for background tiles
like this one. so we need to find out object's image and screenX and the screenY
this time we don't need to do this kind of while loop and scan all the tiles like this
but instead... okay we copy only this part
and paste here
and instead of this tile[tileNum].image, just "image"
so this one, the object's image
other than this, it's same so we don't need to change anything
if we know this object... whatever it is...
if we know this object's worldX and worldY
then we can find out it's screenX and screenY based on player's worldX and worldY
and the screen position
so we can draw it on the screen
so let's call this draw method
i'll go to this GamePanel class
since it's drawing so we go to this paintComponent method
yeah i think it should be here, after tile and before player
we're gonna call that draw method in this SuperObject class
but this time we cannot simply call it like this or this
first we need to know what kind of object we are going to draw
so type like this...
so this obj is... this one so SuperObject array
so basically we scan this SuperObject array one by one
we gonna call this draw method
and pass Graphics2D and this GamePanel
yeah that's it
this length is 10 so we're gonna scan from 0 to 9
and check if any object is inside of this array
we need to check if the slot is null or not otherwise we might get a NullPointer error
so make sure to check it
alright so now we should be able to draw objects so let's check
yes, we found a key
this doesn't look so bad
this looks better than i thought
another one
yep another key is here
nothing happens yet though
so two keys are displayed so this is working good
okay let's create some more objects
so first inside of this object package, create a new class
i'm gonna name this OBJ_Door
and i think we can copy this
and the name is "Door"
we're gonna use this name a bit later
and the image is "door"
okay let's create one more class
so i'm gonna create three doors and place around here
and also around here
and also here
and place the treasure chest around here
okay so AssetSetter
i wanna create one more key
and i'm gonna place it somewhere around here
then create 3 doors
and also treasure chest
okay so coordinate
column 10
row 9
and the chest is column 10 and row 7
so let's check this
okay so first let's check the third key
oop i was expecting around here so...
okay so let's check the doors
okay so doors
the first door
the second door
and oh oh
not here it was supposed to be here
the chest is okay so let's adjust the placement
so 2 tiles to the bottom
okay so door is here and the chest is here
so now we got 3 keys, 3 doors and 1 chest
at the beginning of this series, i said we are going to make a simple treasure hunting game
and we are closing to the end of the first chapter of this tutorial
so the idea is... it's very simple
first we pick 3 keys, and open 3 doors, and get the treasure
right now, there is no collision and you can just walk through this door
but we are going to add collision to this door
and change the settings so we can open this door only when you have a key
there are 3 doors, so you need 3 keys
so that's what we're gonna do next
thanks for watching and until next time
[Music]