hi guys, this is RyiSnow
last time, we implemented object collision
and now we can pick up keys and open doors
in this video we will create one more item
then implement music and sound effect
so we are very close to the end of the first half of this tutorial
so first, let's create another object class
inside of this object package, create a class
and name this OBJ_Boots
and we can borrow the format from other object class
so like this one
and change the name
and for the image we use this "boots.png" that we copied in part 7
okay now go to the AssetSetter
and instantiate this boots
so copy this and change the index
okay so the placement...
i want to place the boots around here
so column 37 and row 42
alright then go to this Player class
and we set the object's reaction
add another case
since this is boots, let's increase the player's movement speed
and delete this object
okay let's check this
got the key and the boots
get the boots and the speed up
now we can move faster
you can make it even faster by changing this number like this
but you know moving faster is not always a good idea
so as you can see
if player moves too fast then the control becomes very difficult
so 4 is definitely too fast
so i'm gonna set this 2 or maybe 1 is enough
also as an alternative idea, maybe you can create an item which makes the player slower
like a penalty item or something
it's all up to you so i hope you come up with some interesting ideas
okay now implementing music and sound effect
first, we create another package in the res folder
and i'm gonna name this "sound"
and here i have prepared some sound files
and these are all WAV file
unfortunately the default java library cannot load mp3
so make sure to prepare the sound as WAV file
it's a bit inconvenient but that's how it is
this one is music
it's kind of a theme song of this game
i made this with beatbox
and these are sound effects so copy these files to this package
and create a class in the main package
and name this Sound
okay first, we declare this Clip
we use this to open audio files
and import
and then URL
i'm gonna name this soundURL and use this as an alley
i think 30 is enough
we use this URL to store the file path of these sound files
i'll show you how it's done
okay let's create a constructor
and here we use this URL array
and get the file path
so here we type a file pass
so for this one...
and the second one is...
so we got these file paths
and now we create four methods
and the first one is setFile
alright first, setFile method
we get integer as an argument
and try and catch
and here, we use a class called AudioInputStream
and import
and to this get AudioInputStream, we pass an URL
and we get the index of this sound URL array from here
so this is like a format to open an audio file in Java
so this setFile method is done
so whenever we want to play a sound file we call display method
and what we're gonna do here is...
and for this loop...
and when we want to stop the sound, we call this method
and here we type clip.stop
that's all about this Sound class
let's go to this GamePanel class
and instantiate this Sound class
okay so let's instantiate the Sound class here
and we don't need to pass anything
i'm gonna move this gameThread here
yeah like this
and by the way, we created this worldWidth and worldHeight a long time ago
i thought we're gonna use this eventually
but come to think of it, i can't think of any situation that we use this
so you can delete this if you want
sorry about that
so we instantiated this Sound class
then create three methods in this GamePanel
maybe after this paintComponent
the first one is...
from here, first we're gonna call the setFile in the Sound class
yeah this one
and then call the play method
then call the loop method
so when we play music, first we set a file
then play and then loop
and the next method is...
and for this one we just call this stop method
and finally, playSE
and for this one too we get an integer
and okay here, first we call the setFile again
and pass this index of the array
for sound effects we don't call this loop
because usually sound effect is very short and we don't need to loop it
alright then let's play a music
so this one　"Blue Boy Adventure"
so we call this playMusic method from here maybe
around here
and we're gonna pass integer as an index
and since we want to play this song so the index is 0
so we pass 0 here
so this playMusic method receive 0
and pass 0 to this setFile
and this setFile put 0 in this soundURL
let's check
so now we can hear a background music
[Music]
and next let's play sound effect
so for example
in this Player class, we can play a sound effect when we get this key
so this time we call this playSE method
and index is this one
so this time we will play this coin sound
so the index is 1, so we pass 1 here
and for the door, let's copy this
door sound is this one, the door unlock sound
so we pass 3
and boots
for this one, we're gonna play this power up sound
so the index is 2
so play number 2 sound effect
okay let's check this
got the key
[Music]
speed up
okay let's open the door
[Music]
unlock the door
yep
okay so it's working good
so now we can play music and sound effect
and i think the next video will be the final episode of the first half of this tutorial series
we will implement on-screen UI and complete this little treasure hunting game
thanks for watching and until next time
[Music]